[
  {
    "question": "Which of the following topics could be the focus of a macroeconomic study?",
    "a": "externalities",
    "b": "price discrimination",
    "c": "gross domestic product",
    "d": "monopolies",
    "e": "price ceilings",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term refers to economics involving only value-free judgments?",
    "a": "positive economics",
    "b": "microeconomics",
    "c": "Keynesian economics",
    "d": "normative economics",
    "e": "macroeconomics",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answer choices would MOST likely be the subject of normative economic analysis?",
    "a": "arguing against lower taxes for the rich",
    "b": "quantifying data on an oligarchic market",
    "c": "describing economic interaction between two nations",
    "d": "predicting the effects of changing fiscal policy",
    "e": "graphing the impact of price discrimination in the theater market",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "On which assumption does cost-benefit analysis rely?",
    "a": "opportunity cost",
    "b": "gains from trade",
    "c": "rationality",
    "d": "trade-offs",
    "e": "scarcity",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What basic economic concept is LEAST relevant to consumers?",
    "a": "cost-benefit analysis",
    "b": "opportunity cost",
    "c": "trade-offs",
    "d": "scarcity",
    "e": "gains from trade",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "How would an economist describe voluntary trade?",
    "a": "It is conducted willingly and benefits those involved.",
    "b": "It enables international exchange.",
    "c": "It uses the private sector to facilitate the transportation of goods and services.",
    "d": "It requires barter to be successful.",
    "e": "It benefits one side more.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "When is a resource considered scarce?",
    "a": "It is in high demand.",
    "b": "Its price is extremely high.",
    "c": "It exists in a limited quantity.",
    "d": "It requires a trade-off.",
    "e": "It is deemed so by the government.",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following topics would a microeconomist study?",
    "a": "the relationship between aggregate demand and output",
    "b": "fluctuations in the unemployment rate",
    "c": "a nation’s labor productivity and industrialization",
    "d": "the effects of a price ceiling",
    "e": "the impact of international trade agreements on GDP",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Sky can study for her economics exam or make $20 mowing her neighbor’s lawn. She chooses to study for her exam. Which of the following answer choices BEST matches the feature of this example to its corresponding economic term?",
    "a": "$20 – opportunity cost",
    "b": "mowing lawn - benevolence",
    "c": "time – Pareto efficiency",
    "d": "studying - scarcity",
    "e": "choice - voluntary",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answer choices BEST describes time, labor, and knowledge?",
    "a": "physical commodities",
    "b": "scarce resources",
    "c": "natural goods",
    "d": "human capital",
    "e": "intangible resources",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "How are macroeconomics and microeconomics related?",
    "a": "They are rooted in normative observations.",
    "b": "They share basic assumptions.",
    "c": "They influence fiscal policy.",
    "d": "They analyze the economic development of a single country.",
    "e": "They make similar predictions.",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following topics would a macroeconomist LEAST likely study?",
    "a": "changing interest rates",
    "b": "inflation",
    "c": "seasonal unemployment",
    "d": "exports",
    "e": "drug monopolies",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What definition of efficiency requires minimizing waste?",
    "a": "Keynesian efficiency",
    "b": "productive efficiency",
    "c": "consumptive efficiency",
    "d": "profit efficiency",
    "e": "Pareto efficiency",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following variables do economists consider infinite?",
    "a": "power",
    "b": "desires",
    "c": "knowledge",
    "d": "money",
    "e": "time",
    "correct_answer": "b"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main purpose of economic models?",
    "a": "to capture external variables",
    "b": "to replicate real-world conditions",
    "c": "to project a range of scenarios",
    "d": "to identify key assumptions",
    "e": "to create complex simulations",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following properties describes a perfectly competitive market?",
    "a": "A single buyer can change the price.",
    "b": "The product is differentiated.",
    "c": "A monopoly controls the supply.",
    "d": "Buyers do not know the exact price.",
    "e": "Many buyers exist.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of good sees demand increase during an economic crisis?",
    "a": "excludable",
    "b": "normal",
    "c": "inferior",
    "d": "complementary",
    "e": "substitute",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "What relationship is articulated by the law of demand?",
    "a": "As price increases, quantity demanded decreases.",
    "b": "As price decreases, quantity demanded decreases.",
    "c": "As price decreases, quantity demanded remains the same.",
    "d": "As price increases, quantity demanded remains the same.",
    "e": "As quantity demanded increases, price stays the same.",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following markets is LEAST organized?",
    "a": "NASDAQ",
    "b": "the Chicago Stock Exchange",
    "c": "Sotheby’s auction house",
    "d": "US Treasury auctions",
    "e": "Farmers Market",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following answer choices BEST describes the nature of the demand curve in microeconomic models?",
    "a": "horizontal",
    "b": "inelastic",
    "c": "Pareto efficient",
    "d": "equal to quantity supplied",
    "e": "downward-sloping",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "As citizens of the kingdom of AcDec earn higher wages, demand for alpaca plushies increases. What kind of good is an alpaca plush?",
    "a": "inelastic",
    "b": "staple",
    "c": "commodity",
    "d": "normal",
    "e": "rival",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the focus of microeconomic analyses?",
    "a": "goods and services",
    "b": "governments and individuals",
    "c": "buyers and sellers",
    "d": "supply and demand",
    "e": "banks and businesses",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who does the market for gasoline include?",
    "a": "OPEC nations",
    "b": "only gasoline sellers",
    "c": "externalities from the EV industry",
    "d": "buyers and sellers of gasoline",
    "e": "only gasoline buyers",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor’s change CANNOT lead to shifts in the demand curve?",
    "a": "price",
    "b": "projections",
    "c": "consumer base",
    "d": "tastes",
    "e": "wages",
    "correct_answer": "a"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following results occurs when the price of ramen decreases?",
    "a": "Demand for ramen shifts up.",
    "b": "Supply of ramen shifts to the left.",
    "c": "Demand for ramen shifts to the left.",
    "d": "Supply of ramen shifts down.",
    "e": "Demand for ramen does not move.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is “perfect competition” a useful concept in the field of economics more broadly?",
    "a": "It helps guide multinational business decisions.",
    "b": "It serves as a model to avoid.",
    "c": "It helps to determine fair prices in international trade.",
    "d": "It often appears in the real world.",
    "e": "It acts as a benchmark for real-world markets.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following statements does NOT describe a highly competitive market?",
    "a": "No single buyer can influence the market price of the product.",
    "b": "All sellers display their prices and update them daily.",
    "c": "30% of consumers switch to a different product, but price remains constant.",
    "d": "A shop reduces its prices for a good and consumers of that good increase their consumption at this shop.",
    "e": "There are a limited number of market participants.",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  },
  {
    "question": "What variables are represented on the horizontal and vertical axes of a demand curve, respectively?",
    "a": "quantity demanded and equilibrium unit price",
    "b": "equilibrium price and quantity demanded",
    "c": "quantity demanded and price",
    "d": "price of the quantity supplied and price",
    "e": "unit price and quantity demanded",
    "correct_answer": "c"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following phenomena does the law of demand explain?",
    "a": "total consumer surplus",
    "b": "number of buyers and sellers",
    "c": "elasticity of a demand curve",
    "d": "slope of a demand curve",
    "e": "equilibrium in a market",
    "correct_answer": "d"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which of the following goods is traded in a highly competitive market?",
    "a": "diamonds",
    "b": "insulin",
    "c": "plane tickets",
    "d": "tennis balls",
    "e": "currency",
    "correct_answer": "e"
  }
]

